Guide to the Carl Iver Hovland Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Carl Iver Hovland papers
1941-1961
MS 1353
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
(26 boxes)
Correspondence, reports, writings, research records and memoranda from professional organizations, all related to his work in the field of communications and the modification of beliefs and attitudes. One-quarter of the papers consists of professional correspondence (1943-1959). Principal writers are Leonard S. Cottrell, John Dollard, Irving L. Janis, Frederick Sheffield, Muzafer Sherif and Donald R. Young. Another large section is devoted to his study of the effectiveness of the War Department's training films during World War II. Also included are a series of essays written between 1939-1958, research proposals, and miscellaneous published material.
Hovland, Carl Iver, 1912-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Institute of Human Relations, Yale University.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Correspondence and Reports; II. Organizations; III. War Department; IV. Research; and V. Writings.
Scope and Contents
The Carl Hovland Papers represent Dr. Hovland's career in research, including his work at Yale. Dating from approximately 1937 to 1961, the papers include correspondence, reports, writings of his colleagues, records of his activities in organizations, his research under various foundations, and his writings. Dr. Hovland's role as director of the War Department study on the effectiveness of training films during World War II is especially well-documented, as is his research on communications and attitude change.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Carl I. Hovland (1912-1961) was Yale professor of psychology, 1936-1961; chairman, Department of Psychology, 1945-1951; Director of Experimental Studies and Chief Psychologist in Research Branch of War Department's Information and Education Division during World War II; experimented and wrote about psychological aspects of persuasive communication and concept formation; director, Yale Communication Research Program; consultant for industry, government, and foundations.
Behaviour modification; Communication -- Psychological aspects; World War, 1939-1945; Educators; Psychologists; Cottrell, Leonard S. (Leonard Slater), 1899-1985; Dollard, John, 1900-1980; Hovland, Carl Iver, 1912-; Janis, Irving L. (Irving Lester), 1918-1990; Sheffield, Frederick, 1902-1971; Sherif, Muzafer, 1906-1988; Young, Donald, 1898-1977; United States. War Department; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Psychology
- Correspondence and Reports, Series I
  - Abelson, Robert P., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anderson, N.H., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barry, Herbert, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bell, Elaine, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Berlyne, Daniel E., 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brehm, Jack W., 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brock, T., 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Campbell, Donald T., Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Campbell: Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carper, James, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clark memos, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cohen, Arthur R., 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cottrell, Leonard S., 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - DeVinney, Leland C., 1946-1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dollard, Dr. John, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Feierabend, Rosalind, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Gladstone, Arthur, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Harvey, O.J., 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Howe, Edmund S., 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hunt, Earl B., Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Janis, Irving L., Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Kelley, Harold H., 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Kelman, Herbert C., Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Kurtz, Kenneth H., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Lesser, Gerald, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Luchins, Abraham S., 1952-1957 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Mandell, Wallace, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - McGuire, William, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Moore, Omar K., 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Morrisett, Lloyd, 1954-1957 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Muheenbauer, Anna, Undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Noyes, Dorothy, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Pritker, Henry A., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Pruitt, Dean, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Rosenbaum, Eva, Undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Rosenberg, Undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Sanford, Fillmore H., 1951-1955 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Segall, Marshall H., 1955 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Siegmann, P.J., 1956 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Sheffield, Frederick, 1943-1944, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 41-42)
  - Shepard, Roger N., 1954 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Sherif, Muzafer, 1948-1956 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Sherif, Muzafer, 1951-1957 (Box 4, Folder 45-46)
  - Silverstein, Undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Simon, Herbert A., 1956-1959 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Simpson, Louise, Undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Thistlethwaite, Donald L., 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Wiener, Jerry, Undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Wilcoxon memos, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Wulff, Jepson, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Young, Donald R., 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 54)
- Organizations: Correspondence, Minutes, Reports, Series II
  - American Philosophical Society, 1947-1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - American Psychological Association
    - Army Advisory Committee, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Board of Directors, 1949-1956 (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
    - Distinguished Scientific Contribution Award, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Education and Training Board, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Committee of Departments Offering Doctoral Training, 1950-1957 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Committee on Intraprofessional Relationships in Psychology, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Committee on Publications, 1948-1954 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Committee on Training in Clinical Psychology, 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Division I: General Psychology, 1953-1957 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Division of Industrial and Business Psychology, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Policy and Planning Board, 1947-1951 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Project A (Koch), 1954 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Publications: Reprint Information, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Scientific Development Board, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Talk: Implications of War-Time Communication Research, Undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Annual Review of Psychology, 1948-1956 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Cross-Cultural Research Group, 1955-1957 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Eastern Psychological Association, 1946-1960 (Box 6, Folder 21-22)
  - Experimentalists, 1942-1946 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Joint Research and Development Board, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - National Education Association, 1957? (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - National Research Council: Division of Anthropology and Psychology, 1951-1956 (Box 7, Folder 27-28)
  - National Science Foundation, 1952-1959 (Box 7, Folder 29-31)
  - Psychological Round Table, 1944-1951 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Research Development Board, 1947-1949 (Box 8, Folder 33-34)
  - Research Development Board: Committee on Human Resources (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Science Research Associates, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Social Science Research Council, 1948-1957
    - SSRC - Cognitive Processes Inst., 1957-1958 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - SSRC - Committee on Measurement of Opinion, Attitudes and Consumer Wants, 1946-1949 (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - SSRC - Committee on Problems and Policy, 1949-1951 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - SSRC - Conference on Research in Public Communication, 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - SSRC - Cottrell, Leonard S., Jr., 1957 (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - SSRC - Public Opinion Polls, 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - SSRC - Research Program (Hovland, Simon, Marquis), 1957-1960 (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - SSRC - Smith, M. Brewster, 1953-1956 (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - Society of Experimental Psychologists, 1945-1959 (Box 9, Folder 46-47)
  - Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues, 1943-1954 (Box 9, Folder 48)
- War Department: Studies and Research, Series III
  - Air Research and Development Command, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Army Research, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Attitude Change: Memos, Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Federal Service Forms, 1942-1955 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Human Resources Research Institute: Maxwell Air Force Base, Undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Human Resources Research Institute: Maxwell Air Force Base Air University, 1951-1952 (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
  - Human Resources Research Office, 1952-1954 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Leadership: Army, 1945-1946 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Report of a conference on Germany After the War, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Scientific Advisory Board: Department of the Air Force, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Secretary of Defense: (Office of) Security, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - SSRC Grant: Analysis Wartime Study: Soldier Attitudes, 1945-1950 (Box 11, Folder 13-14)
  - War Department, 1946-1947 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - War Department: Book, 1946-1949 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - War Department "Chapters", 1946-1947 (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Research, Studies, Grants, with Related Correspondence, Series IV
  - Am. Psych. experiment [?], Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - American Telephone & Telegraph Company, 1946-1951 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Bell Telephone Labs, 1947-1957 (Box 12, Folder 3-5)
  - Brehm-Cohen-Sarnoff study, Undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Buros Reviews, 1949-1951 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - "Case" Method, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Communications: Bibliography and Memos, Undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Communications, 1947-1950 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Communications: bibliographies, Undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Communications, Yale Studies in (outline), Undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Concept: Cahill, Undated (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Concept: Hovland, Undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Discussion Group, 1944-1945 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Egypt, 1951 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Experimental Studies in Rote-Learning Theory IX, Undated (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Experimental Studies in Rote-Learning Theory X: Pre-learning Syllable Familiarization and the Length-Difficulty Relationship, Undated (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Ford Center for Advanced Studies in the Behavioral Sciences, 1952-1955 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Ford Foundation, 1951-1954 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - General Electric: Behavioral Research Service, Undated (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - General finance, 1953-1955 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Higher Education as an area for the Ford Foundation Program, Undated (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Higher Thought, 1956 (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Miller Analogies Test, Undated (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Motion Picture study (Bibliographies, Undated (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - National Opinion Research Council: E. L. Bernays Foundation, 1946-1951 (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1945-1955 (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - Rockefeller Foundation: Rusk, Dean, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - Rockefeller Foundation: Willitz, Joseph H., 1950-1952 (Box 14, Folder 30)
  - Russell Sage Foundation, 1957-1960 (Box 14, Folder 31)
  - Social Psychology, Undated (Box 14, Folder 32)
  - Statistics, 1937-1941 (Box 14, Folder 33)
  - University of Chicago Law, 1953-1955 (Box 14, Folder 34)
  - Wonderlic: Pensions, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 35)
  - Wonderlic: Tests, Undated (Box 14, Folder 36)
- Writings, Series V
  - "Assimilation and Contrast Phenomena in Opinion Change Experiments" (talk), 1956 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - "Changes in Attitude through Communication", Undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - "An Experimental Comparison of Conclusion Drawing by the Communicator and by the Audience", Undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - "The Influence of Mass Communication on Attitudes", Undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - "Judgmental Phenomena and Scales of Attitude Measurement: II. Placement of items with individual choice of number of categories", Undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Personnel Psychology (journal), 1947-1956 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - "Phenomena of Apparent Movement", 1949 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - "A Review of Some Behavior Mechanisms", 1939 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Reviews: "Experiments on Mass Communication", 1949-1951 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - "The Role of Primacy and Recency in Persuasive Communication", Undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - "Social Judgment", 1958 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - "Some Basic Processes underlying Reaction to Communication and Attitude Change", Undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Talks: outlines, Undated (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - "What's a General Psychologist?" (Presidential address, Division of General Psychology, 9/6/1954) (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - News Reports, 1951-1953 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous published material, 1951-1953 (Box 16, Folder 16-17)